<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<elements>
  <info>
    <name>Classes (Libris Mortis)</name>
    <description>Base classes and features from LM.</description>
    <update version="1.0.0">
      <file name="classes.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/SageZeMage/aurora-libris-mortis/main/classes.xml"/>
    </update>
  </info>
  <element name="Blackguard" type="Class" source="Libris Mortis" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_BLACKGUARD">
    <description>Blackguard

The world knows paladins to be shining paragons who champion lofty ideals such as compassion, nobility, sacrifice, and valor. Such virtuous figures are symbols to the common people, icons from which they draw the strength and courage to stand fast against the encroaching darkness. Yet in every light a shadow lurks—the brightness of these noble warriors is equaled by the shadow spreading from their sinister counterparts, the blackguards.

Wielders of Negative Emotions

Blackguards are shadow warriors who embrace the power of what most people consider to be a vice or a dark emotion. A blackguard's vice becomes a central focus for that individual's divine power. Dominance, fury, and pride are among the forces that blackguards cultivate to fuel their might.

Because malevolent deities and wicked forces in the cosmos are more likely to hold a vice in esteem, most blackguards are villains. Nevertheless, blackguards who cling to higher ideals do exist. A heroic blackguard might be born when a divine soldier who tries to exemplify virtue cannot control their anger or some other base emotion. Such blackguards are referred to as fallen paladins. Other heroic blackguards cleave to a vice that a non-evil religion or deity promotes as an asset, or they have learned by necessity to turn their negative tendencies into a divine focus so that they can lead productive lives.

The Temptation of Evil

The power of vice is alluring because it offers fewer restrictions than virtue does. Though the power comes easily, a blackguard always faces the worst temptations of his or her vice, as well as that of other negative emotions that echo the vice. Scruples can be hard to maintain in the face of such a lure. A truly heroic blackguard can never give in and take the easy path.

Heroic blackguards have a hard road to travel. Their truly immoral counterparts form orders that actively oppose virtuous knights and cavaliers. Whether or not a specific blackguard is a member of such a dark order, those same knights and cavaliers rarely understand that a person can channel divine power through a vice without becoming debased. The common people rightly fear all blackguards the same way they fear the black knights of legend. A blackguard who uses the divine power of the dreaded vices to combat evil still has difficulty finding a wide array of allies. He or she rarely enjoys a hero's accolades.

Creating a Blackguard

The most important aspect of a blackguard character is their background and how they became a member of this class. Are you a fallen paladin, or did you gain the power of vice via some other method? Did you find yourself unwillingly consumed by negative emotions, or did you willingly plunge yourself into the shadows? Do you seek some sort of positive change, or do you continue to stray closer and closer to evil?

In particular, take a moment to establish the relationship between your alignment and your levels in this class. Are you an evil-aligned that has fully embraced your dark emotions, or are you good-aligned in spite of them? Do you attempt to control your emotions using a structured, lawful approach, or do you channel them in a free, chaotic manner? If you are neutral along either axis, how do you maintain this balance when the shadows continually attempt to eat away at your sense of self?

Quick Build

You can make a blackguard quickly by following these suggestions. First, Strength should be your highest ability score, followed by Charisma. Second, choose the soldier background.

Blackguards and Paladins

When a paladin actively breaks their oath and falls down the path of darkness, the DM may choose to replace their paladin levels with blackguard levels, rather than using the paladin in the Dungeon Master's Guide. Similarly, if a blackguard completes some sort of quest for atonement, they may be able to make a sacred oath that allows them to replace their blackguard levels with paladin levels.</description>
    <rules>
      <grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_SHROUD_OF_SHADOW" level="1"/>
      <grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_UNHOLY_VIGOR" level="1"/>
      <grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_DREAD_SMITE" level="2"/>
      <grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_FIGHTING_STYLE" level="2"/>
      <grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_SPELLCASTING" level="2"/>
      <grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_INURED_TO_DECAY" level="3"/>
      <grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_BLACKGUARD_VICE" level="3"/>
      <grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_ABILITY_SCORE_IMPROVEMENT" level="4"/>
      <grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_MARTIAL_VERSATILITY" level="4"/>
      <grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_EXTRA_ATTACK" level="5"/>
      <grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_DARK_BLESSING" level="6"/>
      <grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_BLACKGUARD_VICE_FEATURE" level="7"/>
      <grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_ABILITY_SCORE_IMPROVEMENT" level="8"/>
      <grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_AURA_OF_HATE" level="10"/>
      <grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_IMPROVED_DREAD_SMITE" level="11"/>
      <grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_ABILITY_SCORE_IMPROVEMENT" level="12"/>
      <grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_VILE_TOUCH" level="14"/>
      <grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_BLACKGUARD_VICE_FEATURE" level="15"/>
      <grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_ABILITY_SCORE_IMPROVEMENT" level="16"/>
      <grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_AURA_IMPROVEMENTS" level="18"/>
      <grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_ABILITY_SCORE_IMPROVEMENT" level="19"/>
      <grant type="Class Feature" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_BLACKGUARD_VICE_FEATURE" level="20"/>
    </rules>
  </element>
  <element name="Shroud of Shadow" type="Class Feature" source="Libris Mortis" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_SHROUD_OF_SHADOW">
    <description>1st-level blackguard feature

You learn to shroud your dark emotions from those that would oppose their usage. You have advantage on ability checks made to mislead others about your true emotions and alignment, and you have advantage on saving throws against effects that allow other creatures to know your alignment or to read your thoughts or emotions.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description>1st-level blackguard feature

You learn to shroud your dark emotions from those that would oppose their usage. You have advantage on ability checks made to mislead others about your true emotions and alignment, and you have advantage on saving throws against effects that allow other creatures to know your alignment or to read your thoughts or emotions.</description>
    </sheet>
    <requirements>[level:blackguard:1]</requirements>
  </element>
  <element name="Unholy Vigor" type="Class Feature" source="Libris Mortis" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_UNHOLY_VIGOR">
    <description>1st-level blackguard feature

You can use your dark power to invigorate yourself. As a bonus action, you can grant yourself temporary hit points equal to your Charisma modifier + your blackguard level. These temporary hit points disappear after 1 minute.

Once you use this feature, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description>1st-level blackguard feature

You can use your dark power to invigorate yourself. As a bonus action, you can grant yourself temporary hit points equal to your Charisma modifier + your blackguard level. These temporary hit points disappear after 1 minute.

Once you use this feature, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.</description>
    </sheet>
    <requirements>[level:blackguard:1]</requirements>
  </element>
  <element name="Dread Smite" type="Class Feature" source="Libris Mortis" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_DREAD_SMITE">
    <description>2nd-level blackguard feature

When you hit a creature with a melee weapon attack, you can expend one spell slot to deal necrotic damage to the target, in addition to the weapon's damage. The extra damage is 2d8 for a 1st-level spell slot, plus 1d8 for each spell level higher than 1st, to a maximum of 5d8. The damage increases by 1d8 if the target is a celestial, to a maximum of 6d8.

Additionally, when you select a Vice at 3rd level, you gain the ability to change the damage type of your Dread Smite whenever you use it. The damage type you can change it to is dependent on your choice of Vice, as listed in the table below.

Vice | Damage Type

Despair | Cold

Domination | Psychic

Fury | Thunder

Pride | Radiant

Treachery | Poison</description>
    <sheet>
      <description>2nd-level blackguard feature

When you hit a creature with a melee weapon attack, you can expend one spell slot to deal necrotic damage to the target, in addition to the weapon's damage. The extra damage is 2d8 for a 1st-level spell slot, plus 1d8 for each spell level higher than 1st, to a maximum of 5d8. The damage increases by 1d8 if the target is a celestial, to a maximum of 6d8.

Additionally, when you select a Vice at 3rd level, you gain the ability to change the damage type of your Dread Smite whenever you use it. The damage type you can change it to is dependent on your choice of Vice, as listed in the table below.

Vice | Damage Type

Despair | Cold

Domination | Psychic

Fury | Thunder

Pride | Radiant

Treachery | Poison</description>
    </sheet>
    <requirements>[level:blackguard:2]</requirements>
  </element>
  <element name="Fighting Style" type="Class Feature" source="Libris Mortis" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_FIGHTING_STYLE">
    <description>2nd-level blackguard feature

You adopt a particular style of fighting as your specialty. Choose one of the following options. You can't take the same Fighting Style option more than once, even if you get to choose again.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description>2nd-level blackguard feature

You adopt a particular style of fighting as your specialty. Choose one of the following options. You can't take the same Fighting Style option more than once, even if you get to choose again.</description>
    </sheet>
    <requirements>[level:blackguard:2]</requirements>
  </element>
  <element name="Spellcasting" type="Class Feature" source="Libris Mortis" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_SPELLCASTING">
    <description>2nd-level blackguard feature

You have learned to draw on divine magic through the strength of your negative emotions.

Preparing and Casting Spells

The Blackguard table shows how many spell slots you have to cast your blackguard spells. To cast one of your blackguard spells of 1st level or higher, you must expend a slot of the spell's level or higher. You regain all expended spell slots when you finish a long rest.

You prepare the list of blackguard spells that are available for you to cast, choosing from the blackguard spell list. When you do so, choose a number of blackguard spells equal to your Charisma modifier + half your blackguard level, rounded down (minimum of one spell). The spells must be of a level for which you have spell slots.

For example, if you are a 5th-level blackguard, you have four 1st-level and two 2nd-level spell slots. With a Charisma of 14, your list of prepared spells can include four spells of 1st or 2nd-level, in any combination. If you prepare the 1st-level spell inflict wounds, you can cast it using a 1st-level or a 2nd-level slot. Casting the spell doesn't remove it from your list of prepared spells.

You can change your list of prepared spells when you finish a long rest. Preparing a new list of blackguard spells requires time spent in silence and contemplation: at least 1 minute per spell level for each spell on your list.

Spellcasting Ability

Charisma is your spellcasting ability for your blackguard spells, since their power derives from the strength of your dark ambitions. You use your Charisma whenever a spell refers to your spellcasting ability. In addition, you use your Charisma modifier when setting the saving throw DC for a blackguard spell you cast and when making an attack roll with one.

Save DC = 8 + proficiency + relevant modifier

Spellcasting Focus

You can use a holy symbol as a spellcasting focus for your blackguard spells.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description>2nd-level blackguard feature

You have learned to draw on divine magic through the strength of your negative emotions.

Preparing and Casting Spells

The Blackguard table shows how many spell slots you have to cast your blackguard spells. To cast one of your blackguard spells of 1st level or higher, you must expend a slot of the spell's level or higher. You regain all expended spell slots when you finish a long rest.

You prepare the list of blackguard spells that are available for you to cast, choosing from the blackguard spell list. When you do so, choose a number of blackguard spells equal to your Charisma modifier + half your blackguard level, rounded down (minimum of one spell). The spells must be of a level for which you have spell slots.

For example, if you are a 5th-level blackguard, you have four 1st-level and two 2nd-level spell slots. With a Charisma of 14, your list of prepared spells can include four spells of 1st or 2nd-level, in any combination. If you prepare the 1st-level spell inflict wounds, you can cast it using a 1st-level or a 2nd-level slot. Casting the spell doesn't remove it from your list of prepared spells.

You can change your list of prepared spells when you finish a long rest. Preparing a new list of blackguard spells requires time spent in silence and contemplation: at least 1 minute per spell level for each spell on your list.

Spellcasting Ability

Charisma is your spellcasting ability for your blackguard spells, since their power derives from the strength of your dark ambitions. You use your Charisma whenever a spell refers to your spellcasting ability. In addition, you use your Charisma modifier when setting the saving throw DC for a blackguard spell you cast and when making an attack roll with one.

Save DC = 8 + proficiency + relevant modifier

Spellcasting Focus

You can use a holy symbol as a spellcasting focus for your blackguard spells.</description>
    </sheet>
    <requirements>[level:blackguard:2]</requirements>
  </element>
  <element name="Channel Divinity" type="Class Feature" source="Libris Mortis" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_CHANNEL_DIVINITY">
    <description>3rd-level blackguard feature

Your vice allows you to channel divine energy to fuel magical effects. Each Channel Divinity option provided by your vice explains how to use it.

When you use your Channel Divinity, you choose which option to use. You must then finish a short or long rest to use your Channel Divinity again.

Some Channel Divinity effects require saving throws. When you use such an effect from this class, the DC equals your blackguard spell save DC.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description>3rd-level blackguard feature

Your vice allows you to channel divine energy to fuel magical effects. Each Channel Divinity option provided by your vice explains how to use it.

When you use your Channel Divinity, you choose which option to use. You must then finish a short or long rest to use your Channel Divinity again.

Some Channel Divinity effects require saving throws. When you use such an effect from this class, the DC equals your blackguard spell save DC.</description>
    </sheet>
    <requirements>[level:blackguard:3]</requirements>
  </element>
  <element name="Channel Divinity: Harness Divine Power" type="Class Feature" source="Libris Mortis" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_CHANNEL_DIVINITY_HARNESS_DIVINE_POWER">
    <description>3rd-level blackguard {@variantrule optional class features}

You can expend a use of your Channel Divinity to fuel your spells. As a bonus action, you touch your holy symbol, utter a prayer, and regain one expended spell slot, the level of which can be no higher than half your proficiency bonus (rounded up). The number of times you can use this feature is based on the level you've reached in this class: 3rd level, once; 7th level, twice; and 15th level, thrice. You regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description>3rd-level blackguard {@variantrule optional class features}

You can expend a use of your Channel Divinity to fuel your spells. As a bonus action, you touch your holy symbol, utter a prayer, and regain one expended spell slot, the level of which can be no higher than half your proficiency bonus (rounded up). The number of times you can use this feature is based on the level you've reached in this class: 3rd level, once; 7th level, twice; and 15th level, thrice. You regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</description>
    </sheet>
    <requirements>[level:blackguard:3]</requirements>
  </element>
  <element name="Inured to Decay" type="Class Feature" source="Libris Mortis" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_INURED_TO_DECAY">
    <description>3rd-level blackguard feature

The negative energy flowing through you makes you immune to disease.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description>3rd-level blackguard feature

The negative energy flowing through you makes you immune to disease.</description>
    </sheet>
    <requirements>[level:blackguard:3]</requirements>
  </element>
  <element name="Blackguard Vice" type="Class Feature" source="Libris Mortis" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_BLACKGUARD_VICE">
    <description>3rd-level blackguard feature

When you reach 3rd level, you gain the vice that binds you as a blackguard forever. Up to this time you have been tempted by your dark emotions, standing along the boundary between light and darkness. Now you choose from one of the Vices detailed at the end of the class description.

Your choice grants you features at 3rd level and again at 7th, 15th, and 20th level. Those features include vice spells and the Channel Divinity feature.

Vice Spells

Each vice has a list of associated spells. You gain access to these spells at the levels specified in the vice description. Once you gain access to a vice spell, you always have it prepared. Vice spells don't count against the number of spells you can prepare each day.

If you gain a vice spell that doesn't appear on the blackguard spell list, the spell is nonetheless a blackguard spell for you.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description>3rd-level blackguard feature

When you reach 3rd level, you gain the vice that binds you as a blackguard forever. Up to this time you have been tempted by your dark emotions, standing along the boundary between light and darkness. Now you choose from one of the Vices detailed at the end of the class description.

Your choice grants you features at 3rd level and again at 7th, 15th, and 20th level. Those features include vice spells and the Channel Divinity feature.

Vice Spells

Each vice has a list of associated spells. You gain access to these spells at the levels specified in the vice description. Once you gain access to a vice spell, you always have it prepared. Vice spells don't count against the number of spells you can prepare each day.

If you gain a vice spell that doesn't appear on the blackguard spell list, the spell is nonetheless a blackguard spell for you.</description>
    </sheet>
    <requirements>[level:blackguard:3]</requirements>
  </element>
  <element name="Ability Score Improvement" type="Class Feature" source="Libris Mortis" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_ABILITY_SCORE_IMPROVEMENT">
    <description>4th-level blackguard feature

You can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.

If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a {@5etools feat|feats.html}.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description>4th-level blackguard feature

You can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.

If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a {@5etools feat|feats.html}.</description>
    </sheet>
    <requirements>[level:blackguard:4]</requirements>
  </element>
  <element name="Martial Versatility" type="Class Feature" source="Libris Mortis" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_MARTIAL_VERSATILITY">
    <description>4th-level blackguard {@variantrule optional class features}

Whenever you reach a level in this class that grants the Ability Score Improvement feature, you can replace a fighting style you know with another fighting style available to blackguards. This replacement represents a shift of focus in your martial practice.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description>4th-level blackguard {@variantrule optional class features}

Whenever you reach a level in this class that grants the Ability Score Improvement feature, you can replace a fighting style you know with another fighting style available to blackguards. This replacement represents a shift of focus in your martial practice.</description>
    </sheet>
    <requirements>[level:blackguard:4]</requirements>
  </element>
  <element name="Extra Attack" type="Class Feature" source="Libris Mortis" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_EXTRA_ATTACK">
    <description>5th-level blackguard feature

You can attack twice, instead of once, whenever you take the Attack action on your turn.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description>5th-level blackguard feature

You can attack twice, instead of once, whenever you take the Attack action on your turn.</description>
    </sheet>
    <requirements>[level:blackguard:5]</requirements>
  </element>
  <element name="Dark Blessing" type="Class Feature" source="Libris Mortis" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_DARK_BLESSING">
    <description>6th-level blackguard feature

Whenever you make a saving throw while you are conscious, you gain a bonus to the saving throw equal to your Charisma modifier (with a minimum bonus of +1).

You can't benefit from this feature and a paladin's Aura of Protection simultaneously.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description>6th-level blackguard feature

Whenever you make a saving throw while you are conscious, you gain a bonus to the saving throw equal to your Charisma modifier (with a minimum bonus of +1).

You can't benefit from this feature and a paladin's Aura of Protection simultaneously.</description>
    </sheet>
    <requirements>[level:blackguard:6]</requirements>
  </element>
  <element name="Blackguard Vice feature" type="Class Feature" source="Libris Mortis" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_BLACKGUARD_VICE_FEATURE">
    <description>7th-level blackguard feature

You gain a feature granted to you by your Blackguard Vice.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description>7th-level blackguard feature

You gain a feature granted to you by your Blackguard Vice.</description>
    </sheet>
    <requirements>[level:blackguard:7]</requirements>
  </element>
  <element name="Ability Score Improvement" type="Class Feature" source="Libris Mortis" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_ABILITY_SCORE_IMPROVEMENT">
    <description>8th-level blackguard feature

You can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.

If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a {@5etools feat|feats.html}.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description>8th-level blackguard feature

You can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.

If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a {@5etools feat|feats.html}.</description>
    </sheet>
    <requirements>[level:blackguard:8]</requirements>
  </element>
  <element name="Aura of Hate" type="Class Feature" source="Libris Mortis" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_AURA_OF_HATE">
    <description>10th-level blackguard feature

You and any allied fiends and undead within 10 feet of you gain a bonus to melee weapon damage rolls equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum of +1) while you are conscious.

At 18th level, the range of this aura increases to 30 feet.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description>10th-level blackguard feature

You and any allied fiends and undead within 10 feet of you gain a bonus to melee weapon damage rolls equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum of +1) while you are conscious.

At 18th level, the range of this aura increases to 30 feet.</description>
    </sheet>
    <requirements>[level:blackguard:10]</requirements>
  </element>
  <element name="Improved Dread Smite" type="Class Feature" source="Libris Mortis" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_IMPROVED_DREAD_SMITE">
    <description>11th-level blackguard feature

Your heart is so suffused with shadow essence that all your melee weapon strikes carry dread power with them. Whenever you hit a creature with a melee weapon, the creature takes an extra 1d8 damage. The damage type of this effect can be necrotic damage, or it can be the damage type associated with your Vice.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description>11th-level blackguard feature

Your heart is so suffused with shadow essence that all your melee weapon strikes carry dread power with them. Whenever you hit a creature with a melee weapon, the creature takes an extra 1d8 damage. The damage type of this effect can be necrotic damage, or it can be the damage type associated with your Vice.</description>
    </sheet>
    <requirements>[level:blackguard:11]</requirements>
  </element>
  <element name="Ability Score Improvement" type="Class Feature" source="Libris Mortis" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_ABILITY_SCORE_IMPROVEMENT">
    <description>12th-level blackguard feature

You can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.

If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a {@5etools feat|feats.html}.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description>12th-level blackguard feature

You can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.

If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a {@5etools feat|feats.html}.</description>
    </sheet>
    <requirements>[level:blackguard:12]</requirements>
  </element>
  <element name="Vile Touch" type="Class Feature" source="Libris Mortis" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_VILE_TOUCH">
    <description>14th-level blackguard feature

You can use your action to make a melee spell attack against a hostile creature within your reach. On a hit, the target has disadvantage on all saving throws until the start of your next turn.

You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Charisma modifier (a minimum of once). You regain expended uses when you finish a long rest.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description>14th-level blackguard feature

You can use your action to make a melee spell attack against a hostile creature within your reach. On a hit, the target has disadvantage on all saving throws until the start of your next turn.

You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Charisma modifier (a minimum of once). You regain expended uses when you finish a long rest.</description>
    </sheet>
    <requirements>[level:blackguard:14]</requirements>
  </element>
  <element name="Blackguard Vice feature" type="Class Feature" source="Libris Mortis" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_BLACKGUARD_VICE_FEATURE">
    <description>15th-level blackguard feature

You gain a feature granted to you by your Blackguard Vice.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description>15th-level blackguard feature

You gain a feature granted to you by your Blackguard Vice.</description>
    </sheet>
    <requirements>[level:blackguard:15]</requirements>
  </element>
  <element name="Ability Score Improvement" type="Class Feature" source="Libris Mortis" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_ABILITY_SCORE_IMPROVEMENT">
    <description>16th-level blackguard feature

You can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.

If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a {@5etools feat|feats.html}.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description>16th-level blackguard feature

You can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.

If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a {@5etools feat|feats.html}.</description>
    </sheet>
    <requirements>[level:blackguard:16]</requirements>
  </element>
  <element name="Aura improvements" type="Class Feature" source="Libris Mortis" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_AURA_IMPROVEMENTS">
    <description>18th-level blackguard feature

At 18th level, the range of your Aura of Hate increases to 30 feet.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description>18th-level blackguard feature

At 18th level, the range of your Aura of Hate increases to 30 feet.</description>
    </sheet>
    <requirements>[level:blackguard:18]</requirements>
  </element>
  <element name="Ability Score Improvement" type="Class Feature" source="Libris Mortis" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_ABILITY_SCORE_IMPROVEMENT">
    <description>19th-level blackguard feature

You can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.

If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a {@5etools feat|feats.html}.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description>19th-level blackguard feature

You can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.

If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a {@5etools feat|feats.html}.</description>
    </sheet>
    <requirements>[level:blackguard:19]</requirements>
  </element>
  <element name="Blackguard Vice feature" type="Class Feature" source="Libris Mortis" id="ID_CUSTOM_LM_CLASS_FEATURE_BLACKGUARD_BLACKGUARD_VICE_FEATURE">
    <description>20th-level blackguard feature

You gain a feature granted to you by your Blackguard Vice.</description>
    <sheet>
      <description>20th-level blackguard feature

You gain a feature granted to you by your Blackguard Vice.</description>
    </sheet>
    <requirements>[level:blackguard:20]</requirements>
  </element>
</elements>
